Resync: Xenzai
www.subscene.com
锲而不舍第一季第3集
Morning.
Percy Malleson.
- 早上好
- Percy Malleson
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.
There he goes. Turd of Turd Hall.
他来了 屎堆里的一坨屎
皇室成员会在11:45准时到达工厂
The royal party will arrive at the
factory at 11.45 sharp.
Whereupon, Her Royal Highness
Princess Margaret will be escorted on
a tour of the works
然后  玛格利特公主殿下会在董事长
Henry Broom先生的陪伴下
参观工厂
by company chairman, Mr Henry Broom.
在超快二号地对空导弹
After the official unveiling
of the new Standfast Mark Two
surface-to-air missile,
正式揭幕及欣赏后
and subsequent viewing and
appreciation of the same...
公主殿下将移驾公司主办公室
her Royal Highness will then repair
to the main company offices
where refreshments and a light
buffet-style luncheon will be
graciously enjoyed.
享用茶点和小型自助午宴
Now, the purpose of this visit
这次参观目的是
促进英国工业在国外的发展
is to help promote British industry
abroad.
To that end, a trade delegation,
所以 哈桑联合王国的
纳比尔殿下带领的
led by His Highness
Crown Prince Nabil
贸易代表团
of the United Hashemite kingdoms
will also be in attendance,
以及海外贸易部的大臣们
都会一同出席
together with ministers from the
Board of Overseas Trade.
我们局非常荣幸地被指定
This station has been awarded
the signal honour
提供这次参观期间的
of providing additional security
额外安全保护
for the duration of the visit.
The world will be watching.
全世界将拭目以待
早上好 伙计
Morning, matey.
How do I look?
我看起来怎么样?
Very... dependable.
I was hoping for "smart" but...
- 很...可靠?
- 我以为你会说"聪明"的 不过...
Been up half the night on these
buttons.
大半夜就起来弄这些纽扣了
不是百代来做报道吗?
The Pathe mob are covering it,
aren't they?
Got to look your best.
得打扮得好看点
第一声"殿下"后要叫Ma'am 是吧?
After the first "Your Highness",
it's Ma'am.
- 跟Spam押韵
- 长官早
To rhyme with Spam.
Sir.
Morse.
Rather than Smarm.
- Morse早
- 比Smarm好
- 什么?
- 押韵啊 长官
What?
To rhyme with, sir.
Mam, not Marm.
押Mam 不是Marm
没错
Just so.
皇室成员预计会在下午两点离开工厂
The royal party is expected to depart
the factory at 1400,
所以我想我们两点半就可以回来了
so I would expect a return to
barracks
by 1430.
- 能做好吧?
- 会尽力的 长官
Manage till then?
Do our best, sir.
你没收到邀请?
皇家露天招待会的
Didn't get your invite, then?
The royal garden party.
还以为你是第一个受邀的呢
Thought you'd have been first
on the guest list.
我的停车位被
站在梯子上挂彩旗的人给占了
My parking space is occupied by
men up ladders hanging bunting.
这也就算了 可我得从车间走
I wouldn't mind but I've just
had to cross the factory floor,
车间还一股子的油漆味
not to mention the whole place
reeks of paint,
all for the sake of
buttering up a few royals.
就为了巴结几个皇室成员
All for the sake of 36 Standfast
missiles.
为的是36枚超快导弹
Three years' output, Johnny,
potentially.
有可能会接到三年订单 Johnny
I thought even you might see
how vital this contract is.
我还以为就算是你
也能看出这合同有多重要
Of course I see.
I just wish we didn't have to
turn the place upside down.
我当然看得出
我只是不希望把这里搞得乱七八糟
Good morning, Brenda.
Morning, Mr Broom.
- 早上好 Brenda
- 早上好 Broom先生
- 要茶还是咖啡?
- 不 不 不用了
Tea, coffee?
No, no, not now.
Here you are, then, Cinders.
You shall go to the ball.
给你 灰姑娘
你可以去舞会了
刚去了趟情报室
Just came into the Information Room.
Bunch of anarchists looking to egg
the royal limo.
一群无政府主义者想往皇室乘坐的车扔鸡蛋
Get down the Broad,
make sure they don't.
- 去Broad街确保他们不妄动
Something for uniform, isn't it?
- 这不是制服警的事吗?
Funnily enough, we're a bit light
on woodentops today,
说来怪了 今天我们的地位没制服警高
所以...动起来
so... chop chop.
There's a piece in Flight
on the visit, quoting Dickie.
Flight上面有一篇访问的文章
引用了Dickie的话
'What's good for British Imperial
Electric is good for Britain.'
Apparently.
"对大英电机公司好就是对大英帝国好"
可不是
噢 早上好 Alice
Oh, morning, Alice.
- 你今天真漂亮
- 谢谢 Johnny
How lovely you look today.
Thank you, Johnny.
- 给公主的?
- 给你太太的
For Her Highness?
For your wife.
- Nora不喜欢剪下来的花
- 花也不爱她
Nora can't abide cut flowers.
Or they her.
Blooms wither at her passing.
她走过的地方花都凋谢了
听说有次一只蠍子扎了她
结果死了
They say a scorpion
stung her once... and died.
Damn! I never liked these things.
见鬼! 最不喜欢搞这些东西了
我来
Here.
- 你太没耐心了
You're all fingers and thumbs.
- 要是没有你我可怎么办 Vexin小姐?
What would I do without you, Miss
Vexin?
Reg Tracepurcel's waiting to see you.
Reg Tracepurcel在等你
Lenny Frost那事
This business with Lenny Frost...
Labour relations is Johnny's purview.
劳资关系是Johnny管的
If you want him to go away,
get Dick to handle him.
如果你想打发他 就让Dick去管
Reg同志最喜欢听轰炸机司令部的故事了
Comrade Reg is a sucker
for tales of Bomber Command.
- Dickie在哪儿?
- 我刚看到他在会议室
Where is Dickie?
Boardroom, last time I looked.
Keep him straight today, Johnny.
别让他喝醉了 Johnny
至少让他撑到大家都走了
At least till everyone's gone.
谢谢 Michael
Thank you, Michael.
Henry.
Nora. Good run?
- Henry
- Nora 一路顺利?
The lights turned green for me
when I asked them to.
我一发话就一路绿灯了
你不需要特地找人来接我
You needn't have gone to all this
trouble.
Thank you.
谢谢
Richard.
Mother.
- Richard
- 妈妈
Bourbon for breakfast?
早餐就喝波旁?
我知道你要来
I knew you were coming.
Hm. Now, where's Little Boots?
小靴靴在哪儿
能不这么叫我吗?
你好
I wish you wouldn't call me that.
How are you?
不能
I endure.
Is Estella not joining us?
Later.
- Estella不来吗?
- 她晚点到
You know your sister has no head
for business. Shall we?
你也知道你姐姐没生意头脑
这边走?
I do hope there are sandwiches.
希望准备了三明治
饿着肚子
There's only so much
obsequious insincerity
I can take on an empty stomach.
收了一堆谄媚和虚伪
他今天已经第二次了
That's the second time he's had that
today.
散了
Hop it.
你以为出现在这里
对你的案子就会有帮助吗?
You really think being found on the
premises is going to help your case?
- 你这会应该在见Johnny先生的
- 延期了
You were gonna see Mr Johnny.
Well, it's been put back.
我没有玩忽职守 Reg
你得跟他们说清楚
I wasn't negligent, Reg.
You've got to tell 'em.
I'll get it straightened. I promise.
Yeah? You'd better.
- 我会处理好的 我保证
- 真的? 最好是
Cos I know who landed me in it.
因为我知道是谁陷害我的
你也知道
And so do you.
警察
City Police.
I don't doubt you're very sincere
我不怀疑你的诚意
但如果你能把平等派这词拼对
but you may get your message across
better
if you go to the trouble
of spelling Levellers correctly.
也许能帮你更好地传达信息
就是这样 欢呼热烈点
That's it. Give them a good cheer.
公主殿下
Your Royal Highness.
照下来 照下来 Charlie
Pictures. Pictures, Charlie.
照片才是最有效的
We can't compete with that lot.
文字已死
The written word is dead.
这是Volk博士
And this is Dr Volk.
就是现在了
This is the moment.
Four! Three! Two! One!
4! 3! 2! 1!
Went well, I thought.
我觉得今天还不错
Did you get any sense from the Arabs
as to how things are progressing?
你有没有了解到那几个阿拉伯人
是什么想法?
Crown Prince Nabil had
one or two questions about...
Nabil皇储有一两个疑问...
Well, whatever it is, I'm sure
Estella distracted him beautifully.
不管他有什么问题
我肯定Estella成功让他分心了
你让他们坐一起就这个目的
That is why you sat them together.
知道每个人都各有用处真好
How nice to know one's good for
something.
So, to what do we owe
this extraordinary convocation
of the Board?
所以 人来这么齐要讨论什么?
I've tabled an agenda.
我提了一个议程
我才不会闭着眼走进陷阱 Henry
I'm not about to sleepwalk my way
into an ambush, Henry.
Where were you going to spring it
on me? Matters arising?
你要用什么借口刁难我? 出了事故?
还有其他的吗?
Any other business?
你没写在文件上的是什么?
What's not in that paper?
别说 让我猜猜
Don't tell me. Let me guess.
是不是跟法国人的合并建议?
The proposed merger with the French,
perhaps?
You may have banished me
from hearth and home,
也许你不把我当自己人了
but I still hold 33% of the company's
stock.
但我还是有公司33%股权
- 不过是少数股份
- 还有我们女儿的代理权
A minority share.
And our daughter's proxy.
Estella's 2%.
Estella的2%
Even a fool could work that one out.
Johnny?
傻子都知道什么意思 Johnny你说呢?
我知道这是什么意思
你可以否决任何提议
I know what it means.
It means you can block any proposal.
如果你不想谈判的话 也不会来这了
You wouldn't have come here
if you weren't willing to negotiate.
说不定我就是喜欢
看公主是怎么拿叉的
Perhaps I just fancied seeing
how a princess holds her fork.
Her Royal Highness put everyone
quite at their ease.
公主殿下没有让大家感到紧张
A marvellous quality, don't you
think?
人真好 你不觉得吗?
She spoke to you, then, sir?
Oh, yes.
- 她和你说话了喽 长官?
- 当然
Protocol dictates of course
that one has to wait
当然 皇家礼仪规定
一定要公主殿下先开口才可以说话
当然是这样 不过...
for Her Royal Highness
to speak to one first.
Morse, phone.
Morse 接电话
你来这远吗? 她说
'Have you come far?' she said.
Just like that. Regular, familiar as
you please.
就这样 平常又亲切
CID. Morse.
'Have you come far?'
- 刑事调查科Morse
- 你来这远吗?
What did you say?
That I hadn't.
- 你怎么答的?
- 我说我不是
值得铭记 长官
One for the memoirs, sir.
没错 这次活动没出一点差错
我们都应该感到骄傲
Yes. I think we can all take pride
that everything went off
without the slightest hitch.
是大英电机公司 长官
That was British Imperial, sir.
工厂发现一具尸体 疑似谋杀
A body's been found at the factory.
Looks like murder.
Richard Broom 总警司 我是厂长
我们刚见过了
Richard Broom, Chief Superintendent.
Works Manager. We met earlier.
Stay here. No-one in or out.
留在这儿 不准任何人出入
The name of the deceased
is Malleson, Percy Malleson.
死者叫Malleson
Percy Malleson
He's been with us about six months.
他在这儿工作了将近六个月
As what?
General fitter.
- 什么职位
- 普通流水线工人
做机身组装的
Worked on fuselage assembly.
- 可靠吗?
- 可靠
Reliable?
Yes.
Good timekeeper.
No complaints about his work.
很守时 从不抱怨工作
- 谁发现他的?
- 我爸爸的私人秘书
Who found him?
My father's personal assistant.
就...就在这里面
It's er... It's just in there.
可是 他在这儿干什么...
Though, what he was doing here...
When was he found?
About an hour ago.
- 什么时候发现他的?
- 差不多一小时前
All right, Mr Broom.
We'll take it from here.
好的 Broom先生
这里我们接手了
别走太远
我们目前还需要你的协助
Don't go too far. I'm sure we'll be
needing you presently.
你好 DeBryn医生
Dr DeBryn.
Gentlemen.
What have you got?
- 各位好
- 有什么发现?
正如你们所见 地方狭小
Not enough room to swing a cat,
as you can see.
What is that? A screwdriver?
那是什么? 螺丝起子?
Driven into the right ocular orbit
with some considerable force.
被人用力插进了右眼眶
Death would have been instantaneous?
More or less.
- 是瞬间致死吗?
- 差不多吧
不可能是意外?
No chance it could've been an
accident?
除非他可以自己把自己的尸体拖进来
Not unless he picked himself up
and dragged himself in here.
壁脚板和墙上都有血
There's blood on the skirting and on
the wall.
Any idea what time? Body temperature
suggests about four hours ago.
- 知道死亡时间吗?
- 据体温判断应该是四小时前
Certainly not so much as five.
- 肯定没有五小时
- 刚好是公主殿下到达的时候
Just about the time
Her Royal Highness arrived.
Well, that's one suspect
we can rule out at least.
至少可以排除她的嫌疑了
- 这事不好笑 Thursday
- 是的 长官
Hardly a matter for levity,
Thursday. No, sir.
But we were charged with
protecting her security.
但当时我们正在保护她的安全
我觉得那项任务执行得非常优秀
That duty was discharged admirably,
as far as I can make out.
Whatever else happened here,
no blame can attach to the station.
不管这里发生了什么
都不会连累到警局的
你是指我吧
Me, you mean.
我想警队可不会轻易放过这事
I doubt Division will take
so charitable a view of things.
肯定要通知皇室
The Palace will have to be notified.
麻烦大了去了
Whole to-do's a complete bloody mess.
Watch what you're doing, Morse.
For God's sake.
看着点 Morse 真是的
Oops.
哎呦
There is one other thing. Not that
it's likely to be much use to you.
还有一样东西
不一定对你有多大用处
这个是在他口袋里发现的
But this was in his pocket.
Is it murder?
是谋杀吗?
Yes, madam. It would appear so.
Hm.
是的 女士 看起来是
- 我的天 "当麻烦来临..."
- 什么?
My God. "When troubles come..."
Sir?
We're in the middle of some...
very delicate business discussions.
我们正在进行非常棘手的业务讨论
这事真心为公司带来很多不便
This really couldn't be more
inconvenient for the company.
Rather more than inconvenient
for the victim, wouldn't you say?
对被害者来说可不仅仅是不便
你觉得呢?
谢谢你 警员
我觉得我和Thursday督察
Thank you, Constable. I think
perhaps myself, Inspector Thursday
加上Jakes警长应该足够处理这里了
and Sergeant Jakes are sufficient
manpower to the task at hand.
If you'd like to wait outside.
你去外面等着吧
The victim was a fitter, you said.
That's right.
- 你说被害者是装配工?
- 是的
那他工作的时候不需要秒表吧?
He wouldn't have used a stopwatch
in his work?
- 秒表?
- 在尸身上发现的 长官
A stopwatch?
One was found on his body, sir.
不用 反而搞科研的人
No. That's more the sort of thing
比较可能会带一个在身上
one would expect to find
the research boys carry around.
But, fuselage assembly? No. No need
for it, I shouldn't have thought.
但是 机身组装?
不 不需要 我认为不需要
If there was nothing else?
Sir.
- 没其他了吧?
- 是的 长官
I'm going to need an account from
each of you as to your movements
between 10.30 and 12.
我需要你们每一位
10点半到12点之间的动向说明
我们? 这肯定是工人间矛盾啊
From us? This will be some falling
out on the shop floor, surely.
Over money, or... a girl or something.
为钱 为女人什么的
Talk to Tracepurcel.
Reg Tracepurcel. Shop steward.
跟Tracepurcel谈谈
Reg Tracepurcel 工人代表
He knows the ins and outs of these
people. At least he should do.
他知道工人的详细情况
这是他分内的事
- 工会雇他就是为了这个
- 死的是谁?
What the union pays him for.
Who is it's died?
你不会认识的 叫Malleson的人
You wouldn't know him.
A man called Malleson.
Percy Malleson? 机身组装?
Percy Malleson? Fuselage assembly?
- 我看过工资单
- 你?
I was casting an eye
over the payroll. You were?
Yes, my interests do extend beyond
the realm of Horse and Hound.
很难相信 我知道
我的兴趣不仅仅是骑马打猎
Since when?
什么时候的事?
我没听说过他
Well, I've never heard of him,
I'm afraid.
It's impossible to know
all their names.
根本不可能记住全部人的名字
- Harry可以
- 我已故哥哥
Harry did.
My late brother.
He was very good like that.
The common touch.
他很擅长这个 平易近人
Can I help you?
Police.
- 有什么可以帮你吗
- 警察
Miss...?
小姐...?
Morse?
Alice? Alice...
Vexin.
Vexin
- 没错
- 我以前住在Susan对面
Of course. I was across the stair
from... Susan.
Oh, yes. I remember. Erm...
噢 对 我记得 呃...
Yeah. Forgive me, you've erm...
不好意思 你...
- 你换了...
- 噢 是吗?
Changed your...
Oh. Have I?
- 我想是的
- 不好意思 我刚没认出你
I imagine I must.
Forgive me, I didn't recognise you.
No earthly reason you should.
I suppose not. Six years.
- 没理由你该记得的
- 是啊 六年了
Seven.
七年
我记得是 再说了 我们不过才见过六次
I think. Besides, we only met
half a dozen times.
真正见面那种
Properly, anyway.
不过我记得有个星期天
你 我还有Alex Reece
Though I think Alex Reece and I
made a four once
and came upriver
with you one Sunday.
一起去上游玩赛艇
That's right. Good heavens.
没错 天呐
It poured all afternoon.
Do you remember?
下了一下午的雨 你还记得吗?
- 记得
- Morse
Yes.
Morse.
我同事 Jakes警长
Alice Vexin小姐
My colleague. DS Jakes.
Miss Alice Vexin.
You're the one found the body.
是你发现的尸体
我们会找你了解情况的 小姐
不要随意走动
We're going to need to talk to you,
Miss. Don't go anywhere.
Morse?
Well, it was...
- Morse?
- 很高兴...
Despite the er...
You too.
- 虽然...
- 我也是
You know her? We were up at
the same time. At Oxford.
- 你认识她?
- 我们在牛津是同窗
I know what "up" means.
我知道同窗是什么意思
- 女朋友吧?
- 为什么这么说?
Girlfriend, was she?
What makes you say that?
因为她看你的眼神
Way she looked at you.
Tell you - play your cards right,
mate, you're on a promise there.
跟你说 见机行事 你有机会的
Nice bit of homework too.
还有 动作要亲昵点
Don't do yourself any favours, do
you?
你存心不让自己好过是不是?
无所畏惧也不心存侥幸
我们工作性质不就是这样吗?
Without fear or favour. Isn't that
the job?
从现在开始 你负责调查工厂
Well, for now, your job's statements
and particulars from the factory
side.
我们要知道在10点半到12点间
We need to know where everybody was
大家都在哪里干什么
and what they were doing
between half-ten and noon.
How many?
Few hundred.
- 多少?
- 几百个
这样你就不能顽皮啦
Should keep you out of mischief.
Good evening, sir.
晚安 先生
Anyone he'd had a falling out with,
do you know?
知道他跟谁起过冲突吗?
So you also work on fuselage
assembly, is that right?
你也是做机身组装的 对不对?
Yeah. And how well did you know
Mr Malleson?
- 对
- 你跟Malleson先生有多熟?
"早上好" "晚上好" 他话不多
"Morning." "Evening." He didn't have
much to say for himself.
他准时上下班 就这样
He clocked on, clocked off. About it.
Anyone on his section
he was particular pals with?
他在车间里有什么朋友吗
- 他吃午饭也是一个人?
No-one he sat with regularly at
lunch?
Like I say, he didn't go out of his
way to mix.
- 我刚说了 他不社交的
好吧 谢谢 你可以走了
All right. Well, thank you.
That's all for now.
You got everything you need, sir?
Yes, thank you, Mr Tracepurcel.
- 还顺利吧 警官?
- 是的 谢谢 Tracepurcel先生
How many more?
It's about halfway through.
- 还有多少?
- 差不多过半
但我可以告诉你 不可能是我的人干的
But it won't be any of my members,
I can tell you that.
They're good blokes.
This'll be someone off site.
他们都是好人 肯定是工厂外的人干的
The one day the place is packed
with strangers and this happens.
厂里一来陌生人就出了这事
谁都有可能溜进来
Any bugger could've wandered in.
我说这话并不是要对你无礼
I don't mean this to be
disrespectful,
但当时你们是负责安保工作的人
but it was your lot that had the
security of the place.
阿拉伯人10点半左右到的
我就在Henry的办公室消遣了一下
The Arabs arrived at about 10.30, so
I amused myself in Henry's office.
- 怎么消遣的?
- 玩牌
Doing what?
Playing Patience.
Happily, a game at which I excel.
That was till what time?
- 这游戏我很擅长 玩得很开心
- 玩到几点?
Estella来的时候 差不多11点一刻
About a quarter past eleven -
when Estella arrived.
The meeting broke up
shortly afterwards,
接着马上就散会了
and we all went across
to greet Her Royal Highness.
然后都出去迎接公主殿下了
- 你和Broom先生分居了
- 有十年了
You and Mr Broom live apart, I
understand. For the past ten years.
I have a place outside Stratford.
我在Stratford外有个房子
不过在这事解决之前
我会待在Chinon Court
Though until this matter is resolved
I shall be staying at Chinon Court.
The family home.
就是我们家
- 下一个请进
- 去吧
Next, please.
In you go.
I'll be with you in a moment.
你稍等
This is an inefficient methodology.
这方法效率太低
- 你是?
- Werner Volk博士
You are?
Doctor Werner Volk.
我负责超快导弹项目的
I'm in charge of
telemetry and guidance systems
for the Standfast Missile Program.
遥测技术和制导系统
My unit is scientific, you
understand?
我部门是搞科学的你知道吗?
I have nothing to do with
the labour force,
跟劳工完全没关系
因此我也不认识死者
therefore I did not know
this dead man.
So... I may return to my work?
所以...我可以回去工作吗?
I just need to establish
where you were
我只想知道
10点半到12点间你在哪干什么
and what you were doing
between 10.30 and noon.
工作 一直到差不多11点50
Working. Until perhaps
ten minutes before 12,
when I left my section and walked
across with everyone else
然后我离开办公室和大家一起
去迎接公主殿下
for the meeting of
Her Royal Highness.
Did you go anywhere near the fuselage
assembly shed or the office block?
你是否去过机身装配车间
或者办公大楼附近?
没有 告诉你了
No. As I told you,
I have nothing to do with
the labour force. Or the office.
我跟劳工或者管理层都没关系
Perhaps if you write my answers
down,
如果你把我的回答写下来
you will not need
to repeat the question.
你就不需要重复问我了
How was it you came to be on
the shop floor, Miss Vexin?
你为什么会在车间 Vexin小姐?
It's a short cut from the office to
the canteen.
那里是从办公室到餐厅的近路
I was just on my way down the back
corridor when... I heard a door slam.
我正好走到走廊后面 然后...
我听到了关门声
And I...
然后我...
It's all right. Take your time.
没事 慢慢说
我发现储藏室的门开着
I noticed the store cupboard door
was open.
I went to close it,
and that's when I saw the blood.
我去关 就看见了血
然后我打开门 看到了他
So, I opened the door...
and there he was.
Who else uses that short cut?
Most of the office staff, I'd have
thought.
- 还有谁会走那条近路?
- 大部分办公室工作人员
走路只要5分钟
Or it's a five-minute walk around the
block.
But you didn't see anyone else
on the shop floor?
但你在车间没有看到其他人?
No. No, I didn't. Thank goodness.
不 没看到 还好没看到
Listen, I just wanted to say thanks,
for getting me in on this.
我就想说声谢谢
让我跟你一起做事
全部都来了呀
Oh. All hands.
那你是怎么看的?
What do you make to it, then?
Well, I think if I was going to
murder someone...
我觉得 如果是我要杀人
I wouldn't do it in a factory
that was crawling with police.
我不会在一个满是警察的工厂动手
So... why here? Why now?
所以...为什么是这里? 为什么是现在?
为什么是今天?
Why today?
- 很了不起是吧?
- 是非常吓人
Magnificent, isn't it?
Terrifying, certainly.
Are you making progress
with your investigation?
你调查有什么进展吗?
不是针对你们 但是你们的离开
会让我们感到很高兴
Nothing personal, of course,
but we'll be glad to see
the back of you.
- 噢 对生意不好
- 事实上 对英国不好
Oh. Bad for business.
Bad for Britain... actually.
我们家族从三十年战争开始一直为国家
My family has supplied this nation
with arms and ordnance
提供武器和军械(1618-1648年欧洲大规模战争)
since the Thirty Years' War.
From Bunker Hill to Balaclava...
I know the history, Mr Broom.
- 从Bunker Hill到Balaclava...
- 历史我还是知道的 Broom先生
那你就应该明白
这次买卖不仅仅关系到公司
Then you should understand... this
sale is not just about the company.
而是关系到国家 我们在国际上的地位
It's about the country.
Our place in the world.
I'm sure all concerned want to see
the matter resolved quickly.
我相信所有相关人员都希望这事尽快解决
And with as little fuss as possible.
而且越低调越好
Dr Volk.
Volk博士
Hullo again.
又见面了
They've let us go. Me, anyway.
他们放我们走了 我是指我
I gathered.
想到了
我倒是想邀你喝一杯
但可能不...
I'd say let's have a drink,
but that's probably not...
不行 但是...要不等案子结了吧
No. But... maybe when it's all done.
Really? I'd like that. Catch up.
真的? 好啊 到时候见
Morse, you mustn't think badly of
them. They're all right, really.
Morse 你别对他们印象太差
真的 他们人还蛮好的
只不过他们不太能接受Harry的死
It's just... They took Harry's death
very badly.
- 什么时候的事
- 四年前
When was that?
Four years ago.
脑子里有个瘤 某天上班的时候突然就去了
Some sort of aneurysm in the brain.
Just keeled over at work one day.
他们都很伤心
They were all heartbroken.
But I think Henr- Mr Broom Senior -
most of all.
但我觉得Henr...老Broom先生
尤其是他
He'd been looking to Harry
to take over the company.
他是想要Harry接手公司的
You must let me give you a lift.
I don't want to take you out of
your way.
- 我送你
- 不顺路别麻烦了
完全不 今天发生了那么多 我坚持
Not at all. After the time
you've had, I insist.
新款Bellini
7秒内就能加速到60
The new Bellini.
Nought to 60 in under seven seconds.
Time and motion? I think that's what
the stopwatch was for.
- 动作计时?
- 我觉得秒表是用来算这个
Timing his mates to see how long
they took with their work.
算他同事完成工作要花多久
Reporting any that were slacking
to management.
举报偷懒的
- 那他交不到朋友吧
- 他人际关系本来就不好
That couldn't have made him
very popular. I don't think he was.
Malleson seems to have kept himself
to himself. Didn't go out drinking
with his workmates.
Malleson好像拒人于千里之外
也不跟同事一起出去喝东西
Fancy.
All right, Sergeant.
- 有趣
- 够了 警长
- 我对他印象是没人喜欢他
- 那枪的事就说得通了
I got the impression he wasn't much
liked. That might explain the gun.
在他午餐盒里找到一把枪
Found a pistol in his lunchbox.
Along with a little notebook
keeping tabs on the Brooms.
还有一本记着监视Broom一家人的笔记本
Keep that under your hat for now.
暂时记得保密
What the hell's he doing bringing a
gun to work?
他为什么要带枪上班?
我们在想他家人或许会知道
We thought his family
might have an idea
but there's none listed on
his employment form.
但他雇佣资料里没填
要不你去他住的地方看看
Maybe you should give his lodgings
the once-over.
有些工人觉得Malleson是走狗
Some of my members were of the
opinion that Malleson was a stooge.
管理层放来的内奸
For the management. A quisling, if
you will.
动作计时员 你怎么看?
A time and motion man. What was your
view?
I wasn't entirely convinced.
我也没有很确定
But we have got an ongoing
dispute over health and safety.
An accident on the shop floor.
但我们在健康和安全问题上一直有争议
因为车间发生了意外
If management discovered evidence
of working malpractice
如果管理层找到工作失职的证据
they'd have a strong bargaining chip
at the negotiating table.
谈判的时候他们就有足够还价的筹码
That's about the size of it, sir.
就要看筹码大小了 警官
天天都这样! 我受够了!
Every day! I'm sick of it!
Bloody pawing! This is meant to be a
place of work.
杀千刀的咸猪手! 这里应该是工作的地方
All right, Brenda love. Calm down.
好了 亲爱的Brenda 冷静
你试试每次经过都被摸屁股
You have 'em grab your arse
every time you go by,
总要性骚扰你 看你喜不喜欢
try and touch you up -
see how you like it.
不过就是被调戏一下
又不会掉块肉
It's just a bit of cajolery.
Nobody is getting hurt.
我就知道你会帮他们
你也不是好人
I might've known you'd stick up for
'em. You're no better.
All right. Get yourself an eyeful
every chance.
- 够了
- 找到机会就占便宜
Men - you're all the bloody same!
男人他妈都一样!
All right, thank you, Brenda,
on your way.
好了 谢谢 Brenda 你好走了
别自找麻烦
Don't be making trouble for yourself.
抱歉 两位 她平时表现不错的
来姨妈了吧
I'm sorry, gents, she's usually
good as gold. Full moon.
我了解到你们和工会
I understand you've had some
problems with the union
因为工厂安全记录问题有不愉快
over the factory's safety record.
最近有间机房发生了意外
There was an accident recently
in one of the machine sheds.
有个叫Curtis的小子胳膊被碾了
A chap called Curtis
got his arm crushed.
His colleague's fault - man by the
name of Frost, Lenny Frost.
是同事的错
一个叫Frost的男人 Lenny Frost
No malice in it,
just a moment's inattention.
不是故意的 就是一下没注意
But he's suspended, pending the
Factory Board of Inquiry's findings.
但他被停职了
在等工厂调查委员会的结果
工会威胁除非Frost复职不然就罢工?
The union's threatening action
unless Frost is reinstated?
The union is always threatening
action, Inspector.
工会一直都在威胁罢工 督察
A fact of modern business life.
现代商业生活就是这样
虽然如此 但我想出售谈判在即
Nevertheless,
a strike's the last thing you need
with this sales negotiation
going on. It won't come to that.
- 你最不想看到的就是罢工吧
- 不会到那一步的
It's been suggested Mr Malleson may
have been put on the shop floor
有人说Malleson先生
可能是管理层派去车间
- 用来举报同事的
- 谁说的? Tracepurcel?
by management to report on his
colleagues. By whom? Tracepurcel?
放他个屁 其他工厂也许会出这种事
Bloody red. Look, that sort of thing
may go on in other factories,
but that's simply not the way
things work any more.
但现在都不干这种事了
现在首要嫌疑人是一个叫Frost的人
长官 Lenny Frost
Front runner at the moment is a lad
called Frost, sir. Lenny Frost.
From what we've picked up,
Malleson landed him in it.
从查到的资料看 Malleson举报了他
- 私人恩怨?
- 剩下的大部分工人都被我们排除了
Private grudge? We've ruled out
most of the rest of the workers.
但说到这一家人
没一个人有完美不在场证明
But as far as the family's concerned
there's not one of them with
a watertight alibi.
他们一家人? 他们能有什么动机?
The family?
Why would they wish him harm?
Malleson在调查他们
Malleson had been keeping them
under observation.
To what end?
Not clear yet, sir.
- 为了什么?
- 还不清楚 长官
但是车间到办公楼有个走廊
But there's a corridor
to the office block.
随便谁只要几分钟
It wouldn't have taken anyone more
than a few minutes
to kill Malleson
and hide the body.
就可以杀了Malleson然后藏尸
Or someone visiting, of course.
There were enough guests there.
当然还可能是来访的人
宾客挺多的
我在试着安排跟Nabil皇储见一面
I'm trying to arrange a meeting
with Crown Prince Nabil,
though what connection his party
might have to Malleson...
但他的人跟Malleson会有什么关系就...
不管做什么 小心处理 嗯?
Well, whatever you do,
tread lightly, hm?
It's not just matters of business
at stake here,
不仅仅是生意问题在成败关头
but er... matters of state.
还有...国家问题
会谨慎处理 长官
Kid gloves, sir.
Is that the Assistant Chief
Constable's car I saw earlier?
我之前看到的那是助理警察局长的车吗?
34 years.
34年
如果这事传到了皇室
If this matter touches the Palace,
I've been left in no doubt as to
where the buck will come to rest.
我也就只能卸甲归田了
都说旅行挺好的
It's awfully nice to go travelling,
as they say.
真抱歉 我以后要去的地方都计划好了
You'll excuse me,
but I've hung out all the flags
I'm going to for one day.
Might we forego the amateur
traumatics this evening, hm?
Some hope.
- 今晚能不提不愉快的往事吗?
- 希望吧
看看我们
一个开心又有爱的大家庭
Well, here we are.
One great big happy loving family.
我们上次全聚一起是什么时候?
When were we all together last?
Don't start.
别说了
I won't have his name dragged through
the muck.
已故的人让他安息吧
- 我说真的 妈妈
- 那是
I mean it, Mother.
Course you do.
Until push comes to shove,
then Richard looks to Richard.
到了紧要关头
Richard也只能靠Richard了
你想怎么伤我都行
You can draw as much blood from me
as you like.
别把Harry扯进来 不然皇天在上 我...
Just leave Harry out of it,
or as God's my witness, I...
怎么? 你要怎么?
Yes? You'll what?
You haven't got it in you.
你没那个胆
一次可以 多了就不行了
可怜孩子
Once, poor darling, but not any more.
Mm...
Len 我们听说
你和Percy Malleson之间有过节
What we're hearing, Len,
is that there was bad blood
between you and Percy Malleson
因为他举报你
on account of him landing you in it
at work.
- 我不知道这事
- 那你今天来这儿干嘛?
I don't know nothing about that.
So what were you doing there today?
你被停职了 不该出现在这附近的
You're suspended. Not meant to be
going anywhere near the place.
You were seen, Lenny.
Yeah, by who?
- 有人看到你了 Lenny
- 是吗 谁啊?
Cos whoever said that's a liar.
不管谁说的都是在骗人
我有老婆 一个孩子
Look, I have a wife, a kid,
another on the way.
老婆还怀了一个
我为什么要冒险去做这种事
You think I'd do something to risk
all that?
他害你丢了工作
He lost you your job.
工作可以再找
There's other jobs.
我也许想过报复...
I might have wanted
to stick one on him...
but murder, no.
但杀人 不可能
You've got the wrong bloke.
你们抓错人了
How did you make out at his
lodging?
你在他住处查到了什么?
亲戚方面没进展
Nothing so far as next of kin
is concerned
but he may have been living abroad.
但他可能在国外生活过
There was a suitcase bearing
a Union Castle Line luggage label.
有个行李箱上粘着Union Castle线路的标签
(1900-1977年欧洲到非洲线路)
是到南非 对不对?
That's South Africa, isn't it?
I'll get them to check their
passenger lists
first thing.
我明天一早就让他们去查乘客名单
Jake说你认识Broom的秘书
Vexin小姐 是吗?
Jake said you know Broom's
secretary, Miss Vexin - that right?
Knew. I've not seen her in years.
认识 很多年没见了
She'd be well placed to know
all the family skeletons, I'd think.
我觉得她应该对这个家族的事了如指掌
See what you can get out of her.
She's a friend.
- 你看看能不能套出什么
- 她算是个朋友
她是嫌疑人
She's a suspect.
- 那这些是什么?
- 可能什么都不是
What's all this, then?
Well, nothing. Probably.
Nothing with you usually means
something. So, out with it.
你一般说没什么
通常就是有什么 说吧
Well, it just struck me as odd,
that's all.
我就是觉得奇怪罢了
Malleson家还有一双一样的
There's another pair of these
at Malleson's flat.
Cribb & Co.
Cribb&Co
There can't be that many
on the assembly line at BIEC
工厂流水线工人没几个穿得起手工制鞋吧
你觉得呢
wearing handmade shoes.
We had nothing to hold him on.
I thought you had a witness.
- 我们没证据扣留他
- 我以为你有证人看到他在工厂出现了
刚打电话撤销证词了
Rang through to withdraw
their statement.
什么情况? 工会搞鬼?
What's this? Union skulduggery?
Possibly.
There's no "possibly" about it.
- 有可能
- 没什么可能不可能
如果Malleson是个动作计时员传出去了
If it's got around that Malleson
was a time-and-motion man,
他们就不牺牲自己人了
they're not about to let
one of their own swing for it.
他们团结一致
#They'll close ranks.
So, we're back to square one.
所以 我们又回到起点了
噢 威尔士亲王
(英国王储称号 此为鞋款)
Oh, Prince of Wales.
这模型我有...十年没做过了
Haven't made this particular model
for about... ten years.
这顾客一定是个品味和鉴赏力一流的绅士
The customer is clearly a gentleman
of great taste and discernment.
Yes, well, it's well-cared-for.
嗯 保养得很好
尺码八号半
Size eight-and-a-half.
Erm...
噢 有趣!
Oh, interesting!
We've built up the instep quite
considerably to afford support.
我们在覆盖脚背部分做了处理
让它可以更好地撑起来
穿着更舒适
An additional comfort.
Oh, yes, I should be able to
chivvy him out for you.
好 我应该可以帮你把他找出来
我跟代表团在10点20分到达
I arrived with my delegation
at twenty past ten.
We went into the meeting.
然后去开会
That lasted about an hour.
开了差不多一小时
然后我们就去看新超快导弹揭幕
And then we went across for the
unveiling of the new Standfast.
你的人里有中途离过场的吗?
Did any of your party leave
the meeting at any time?
杀一个英国工人对我们有什么好处吗?
What would I or my people have to
gain from killing a British workman?
当然 我会去问
I will ask, of course.
But to the best of my recollection,
no.
但据我回忆 没人离场
We were guests
我们是来宾
从头到尾都跟主办人在一起
and in the presence of our hosts
at all times.
We make a last for each of our
customers
我们帮每一个客户制作了鞋楦
考虑到人脚的特质...
taking into account any
idiosyncrasies of the foot...
Hallux valgus. Polydactyli.
Syndactyli.
拇指外翻 多趾 并趾
Rather like fingerprints.
跟指纹有点像
Ah...
是Malleson吗? Percy Malleson?
Malleson, would it be?
Percy Malleson?
No. This is Mr Kendrick.
不 这是Kendrick先生
Eustace Kendrick
Eustace Kendrick.
看地址是Curtmantle的学生
A student at Curtmantle,
by the address.
没错 他53年5月在这儿做了两双
Yes, he had two pairs off us
in May '53.
Oh, it would appear the bill is still
outstanding.
还没结账的
Oh. Yes, of course, that Kendrick.
哦 是了 那个Kendrick
跟那个...叫Rix的女孩一起
The business with the um...
with the Rix girl.
Well, it was all over the papers.
那时候报纸上满是报导呢
Scotch. That's right, isn't it?
苏格兰威士忌 没错吧?
这是干嘛? 示好?
What's this?
Cessation of hostilities?
We're on the same side, Morse.
我们可是一边的 Morse
有什么收获?
So, any luck?
Olive Rix那案子可是我在邮报的
第一批署名新闻之一
The Olive Rix case was one of
my first bylines at the Mail.
但那是郡里的案子
But it was a County investigation,
不是市警察该管的
和你有什么关系?
not City Police.
What's your interest?
和我查的案子有关
现在爆料的时机不成熟
Just something I'm looking at.
Too early to say.
- 如果有新进展 第一个给你
- 独家?
If anything comes of it, you'll have
it first. Exclusive?
I can't promise.
这我不能保证
Olive Rix是中部地区Barnardo出来的
(英国巴纳多儿童慈善机构)
Olive Rix was a Barnardo's girl
from the Midlands.
很聪明 进了Bicester农学院
Bright. Got herself a place at
Bicester Agricultural College.
Coronation Day she disappeared.
加冕日失踪
(英国女王伊丽莎白二世加冕)
June 2nd 1953.
1953年6月2号
因为有庆典 几天后
With the celebrations,
it was a couple of days
警察才相信是失踪 立了案
before the police took it seriously
as a missing persons case.
Boyfriend fell suspect.
男朋友有嫌疑
Eustace Kendrick?
That's right.
- Eustace Kendrick?
- 没错
There was some talk he'd got her in
trouble.
有人说他害了她
但指控还没成立 他就出国了
But before charges could be brought,
he left the country.
And Olive?
- 那Olive呢?
- 活不见人 死不见尸
No body was ever found.
What's this all about?
这是怎么回事?
I'd have thought you'd be busy
at British Imperial
我还以为你忙着调查大英公司
现在居然挖起了12年前的失踪案
rather than digging up some
12-year-old missing person's case.
How did you find me?
你怎么找到我的?
原始报告有Eustace母亲的名字和地址
The original report gave a name
and address for Eustace's mother.
A neighbour said she was
in a hospice.
一个邻居说她在护理所
Who gave you my name.
Mm.
- 还告诉了你我名字
- 嗯
Outside of Eustace, Aunt Lavinia
is the only family I have.
除了Eustace
Lavinia姨妈是我唯一的亲人
You're sure it's him?
你确定是他?
We'll need you to make a formal
identification, but I'm afraid
that appears to be the case.
我们需要你做一个正式辨认
但恐怕是八九不离十了
Poor Eustace.
可怜的Eustace
He didn't do it, you know. Olive.
那事不是他做的 Olive
Then why did he run away?
那他为什么要跑?
慌了吧? 才20岁就要面对那么多流言蜚语
Panicked? 20 years old
with everything that was being said.
If it had gone against him,
it would have been the rope.
如果情况对他不利 可能就会定他罪
Of course, once he'd gone...
当然 他一走...
Have you any thought
as to why he might return now,
after all this time?
你知不知道为什么这么多年了
他会选择现在回来?
When Aunt Lavinia took ill,
Lavinia阿姨生病的时候
六七个月前 我在泰晤士报上发了个通知
I put a notice in The Times,
six, seven months ago,
- 希望他能收到消息
- 他跟她在一起时间长吗? Olive Rix?
hoping word might reach him.
Had he been with her long? Olive Rix?
A few months.
几个月吧
But the situation was... complex.
但情况很...复杂
Olive...本来就跟了个人
Olive was... already involved.
With whom I don't know,
我不知道是跟谁
从点滴看来 好像嫉妒心很强
but from what I could glean,
he sounded the jealous type.
Older, I think.
我觉得应该是上了年纪的人
All I can tell you is
the Eustace I knew...
我只能告诉你我认识的Eustace...
was the gentlest, kindest of boys.
是一个最温柔最善良的男生
He'd never have done
anything to that girl.
他绝对没有伤害过那女孩
Thank you for your help.
谢谢你的帮助
So Percy Malleson is in fact
this Eustace Kendrick?
所以Percy Malleson
实际上是Eustace Kendrick?
Where the hell has he been till now?
那他之前一直在哪儿?
Until most recently, South Africa.
回国之前都在南非
我让Union Castle查了名单
I've had Union Castle check their
lists.
一个叫Malleson的乘客
从Durban坐了Pendennis Castlel线
A passenger called Malleson sailed
from Durban on the Pendennis Castle
and arrived in Southampton
on 5th April.
4月5日到达Southampton
- 他什么时候开始在大英公司工作的?
- 两周后
And he started at British Imperial
when? Two weeks later.
His mother is dying. I think Kendrick
came back to see her.
他妈妈快死了
我觉得Kendrick是回来看她的
And to do that, he'd have needed
to clear his name.
- 为了去看她 首先他需要把罪名洗掉
- 我就是这么想的
That's my reading of it.
他混进大英电机 觉得真正的罪犯在这里
He's got himself in at BIEC thinking
the real culprit's someone there.
他有一本笔记本
记录Broom家族的来来往往
He's keeping a notebook on the Broom
family. Their comings and goings.
Why would Kendrick think this girl's
disappearance
为什么Kendrick觉得这女孩失踪
had anything to do with the Brooms?
跟Broom家族有关?
I don't know, sir,
but I've taken a look
我不知道 长官
但我有去看了Olive Rix上的农学院
at the agricultural college
that Olive Rix attended.
在Bicester 很大
It's a huge place out at Bicester.
但重点是 学校旁边是Chinon Court
But the point is
its land borders Chinon Court.
Where?
The Brooms' estate, sir.
- 哪里?
- 是Broom家族的地产 长官
According to county records,
the family were questioned
at the time of her disappearance.
根据郡记录 她失踪的时候
他们家族还被问了话
加冕日?
Coronation Day?
Well, that's... that's 12 years ago.
那是...那是12年前了
A missing girl, you say?
Olive Rix.
- 你是说一个失踪的女孩?
- Olive Rix
She was 20 years old.
Never heard of her.
- 那时候20岁
- 没听说过
No. As I said.
刚说过了 不认识
根据原始调查文件 你还被问了话
According to the records
of the original inquiry,
you were questioned.
- 是吗?
- 没错
I was?
Yes.
"Henry Broom说 全天没人离开过家
"Henry Broom said: No-one had been
out of the house for the entire day,
due to watching the Coronation
on the television set."
都在电视前看加冕"
Henry? My son, perhaps. Henry Junior.
Henry? 可能是我儿子 小Henry
Harry...我们这么叫他
Harry... to us.
As Miss Vixen's... I'm so sorry,
Vixen小姐...非常抱歉
Miss Vexin's presence will
no doubt will confirm, Inspector,
Vexin小姐就是个例子 督察
my husband is a fool for beauty.
Nora...
- 我老公就喜欢美女
- Nora...
You didn't hire her
for her shorthand.
你雇她不是因为她会速记
Henry喜欢漂亮的东西
Henry likes to surround himself
with pretty things.
骑马 画画
Horses. Paintings.
If he'd have met this girl,
he would have remembered, believe me.
如果他见过这女孩
一定会记得的 相信我
失陪了?
Would you excuse me?
Oh, dear. One just can't get
the staff.
天呐 找个好员工真难
不好意思 但我完全看不出这个叫Rix的女孩
You'll forgive me, but I'm hard
pressed to see what this Rix girl
跟昨天的案子有什么联系
has to do with what happened
yesterday.
死在你工厂里的男人 Broom先生
The man murdered at your factory,
Mr Broom.
你以为叫Percy Malleson那个
The man you knew as Percy Malleson.
其实真名叫Eustace Kendrick
Turns out his real name
was Eustace Kendrick.
他以前是Olive Rix的男朋友
He'd been Olive Rix's boyfriend
and was strongly suspected of being
involved in her disappearance.
是她失踪案的最大嫌疑人
天呐
Good heavens.
That morning, Olive had been working
at Half Farthing Piggery.
加冕日那个早晨
Olive在Half Farthing养猪场工作
她回学校的路要经过Great Wood
Her path back to College may have
taken her through Great Wood.
Your land?
There's a public right of way.
- 你们的地 不是吗?
- 大家都有使用道路的权利
是非法入侵的权利
Public right of trespass.
You're not saying someone here
had something to do with what
happened to this girl?
你不会真的觉得我们家有人
跟这女孩的案子有关系吧?
看起来Eustace Kendrick是这样想的
It would seem Eustace Kendrick
thought so.
现在他死了
And now he's dead.
我们之间没什么的
There is nothing between us.
Nora just likes to...
Nora就喜欢...
说不清 刺激他
I don't know, goad him.
对不起 我不该这么情绪化的
I'm sorry. I shouldn't let it
get to me.
You'd been with the firm four months
when Harry died.
你说你来这里工作四个月以后Harry死了
That's right.
What was he like?
- 没错
- 他是什么样的人?
噢 很有趣的人
Oh. Just great fun.
Most of the time. He had these moods.
大多数时候 他也有闹情绪的时候
The rest of the family
were all very...
他家人在他身边的时候都很...
careful around him at such times.
- 小心翼翼
Any idea what was behind them?
- 知道是什么原因吗?
Oh, I don't know. A girl?
不知道 因为女人?
It's usually the way.
一般都是这个
How long have you been
back in Oxford?
你回牛津多久了?
几个月 你呢?
A couple of months. You?
我没离开过
I never left. Not really.
我读了研 但是...
I started a postgrad, but...
I don't know.
Worked in a bookshop for a while.
说不清 在书店工作了一阵
你念的...
You read er...
历史
History.
- 我以为你...
- 会有所作为
I'd have thought that you...
I'd have done something with my
life.
Yeah. I suppose we all "thought".
嗯 我们都"以为"过
你那之后做了什么?
What did you do? After?
Knocked about a bit. Here and there.
这里去去 那里去去
I was in the army for a while.
我当了一阵子兵
You were... missed.
大家都...很想你
When you left.
I can't think by whom.
- 你走以后
- 没人会想我
No.
是啊
But you were.
但是有人想你
我想我还是...
I suppose I'd better be...
今天晚餐前要跟Nabil王子开个董事会
There's a board meeting ahead of
tonight's dinner with Prince Nabil.
发生了这事 有点...
With everything that's happened,
it's just a bit...
Alice?
你说的那个 出去喝一杯
What you were saying,
about that drink.
我觉得是个好主意
I'm sure it would be all right.
- 真的?
- 老朋友嘛 有什么?
Really?
Old friends. Who could mind that?
也许被问话的是Harry
Perhaps it was Harry who was spoken
to.
- 至少很省事
Convenient, though.
Damned inconvenient for us.
- 可是我们他妈不省事啊
你觉不觉得很奇怪?
It's curious, don't you think?
She disappears on one royal occasion
她在一个皇家庆典时消失
and Kendrick is murdered in the
middle of another.
Kendrick在另一个皇家庆典被谋杀
这里是私人土地
This is private property.
噢 你们来这干嘛?
Oh. What are you doing here?
We've just been up to the house,
Miss Broom.
我们刚去了你家 Broom小姐
问了些问题
关于一个12年前失踪的女孩
Had some questions about a girl
who went missing 12 years ago.
Olive Rix 加冕日失踪的
Olive Rix. The day of the Coronation.
I wouldn't know anything
about that.
我可不知道这种事
She attended the agricultural
college.
她上的农学院
If you regularly rode these woods,
perhaps your paths may've crossed.
如果你经常在这骑马
也许会碰到过她
- 我会避开公共小道
- 我们现在不就在公共小道上吗?
I avoid the public footpath.
On it now, aren't we?
Blucher threw me and bolted. I had
to find him and fetch him back.
Blucher甩下我跑了
我只能去找它 把它牵回来
那Eustace Kendrick呢?
你对这名字有印象吗?
What about Eustace Kendrick?
Does that name mean anything to you?
Should it?
需要有印象吗?
他是Olive的男朋友
He was Olive's boyfriend.
If there's nothing else...
没其它事的话...
你也许会问
一个12年前失踪的女孩
You might ask what a girl who
disappeared 12 years ago
has to do with the murder at the
factory yesterday.
跟昨天工厂谋杀案有什么关系吧
I might. But perhaps such a thing
never crossed my mind.
可能 但也许我从没想过
Perhaps I assume the police know
what they're doing.
也许我以为警察知道他们在做什么
- 或者你压根不鸟这事
- 试试看把我或者我家人牵扯进来
Or you couldn't give a damn.
Try to involve me or any of my
family in this
and you'll discover quite
how much of a damn I do give.
你就会发现我会多鸟这事
那么 你是要告诉我还是不告诉我呢?
Well? Are you going to tell me
or aren't you?
Until yesterday Eustace Kendrick
had been working for BIEC
到昨天为止Eustace Kendrick
under the name of Percy Malleson.
都在用Percy Malleson这个名字
为大英电机工作
好曲折啊
What a tangle.
Down there you've got the piggery.
那里下去就是养猪场
The agricultural college
is over there.
农学院在那边
Give us a shufti at
that snap a minute.
看一眼照片
差不多这里 你觉得呢?
About here, don't you think?
那她在哪里?
She was there, then, hm?
但是问题是她和谁在一起 长官
But who with? That's the question.
Kendrick! 这照片是在他住处找到的!
Kendrick! The photograph
was found in his flat!
听Kendrick的表妹说
Olive当时跟别人在一起
According to his cousin,
Olive was seeing someone else.
Someone else? An older man. Perhaps
Olive had said something to Kendrick
- 别人?
- 一个老男人 可能Olive跟Kendrick说了什么
which led him to believe it might
have been one of the Brooms.
让他觉得可能是Brooms家的人
我们会查出来的 长官
We'll get to the bottom of it, sir.
Don't worry.
I beg your pardon?
- 你别担心
- 你说什么?
Who are you to tell me not to worry?
He only meant, sir...
- 你算什么 叫我别担心?
- 长官 他的意思是...
我知道他什么意思 Thursday
I know exactly what he meant.
不需要你为他找借口! 太无礼了!
I don't need you to make excuses
for him! Damned impertinence!
Hell are you looking at?
You're not going to find the culprit
看什么看? 傻坐着抓不到犯人的
sat about gawking!
Get on with your work, all of you!
全部给老子去工作!
警察回来了
They're back. The police.
Of course. They won't stop till they
get to the bottom of it.
那是当然
不破案他们是不会罢休的
Pa says they're asking about the
Coronation.
爸爸说他们在问加冕日的事
That girl.
那女孩
Turns out... Malleson was her
boyfriend.
原来...Malleson是她男朋友
Oh, yeah. People still talk about
the party they threw at Chinon Court
噢 对 人们到现在还会说起在加冕日
for the workers during
the Coronation,
为工人们在Chinon Court开的派对
不过那时我不在这儿
but before my time, though.
- 你之前在哪工作?
- 邮政总局 做维修
Where were you before?
GPO. Repairs.
15 years.
15年
It's enough to drive you
up the pole.
足够把人搞疯了
当然 我说的是工作!
Which, of course, was the job!
But er... no, it was a grand do,
by all accounts.
但是 不管怎么说 那个派对都很棒
不是说我赞成那些东西 你懂的
Not that I hold with all that,
you understand.
All what?
哪些东西?
君主政体 卑躬屈膝
Monarchy. Bowing and scraping.
You must have enjoyed Her Royal
Highness's visit, then?
公主殿下来访让你不高兴了吧?
Ah, yes. But that's different,
though, isn't it?
嗯 没有 因为这不同 不是吗?
That's about trade, jobs and
people's livelihoods. How's that?
- 那和生意 工作和人们生计有关
- 怎么呢?
This contract with the Arabs could
be very important for the company.
跟阿拉伯人这个合约对公司很重要
36枚超快导弹
36 Standfast missiles.
So if a bit of royalty helps push it
along, I'm all for it.
所以如果皇室愿意推波助澜
我完全没意见
Reg? You'd better come quick.
There's been an accident.
Reg? 快来 出事故了
这他妈是怎么回事?
What the bloody hell's happened
here?
什么事都没有 Tracepurcel先生
Everything's perfectly all right,
Mr Tracepurcel.
Oh, aye, yeah, it looks it.
The brake on the chain-block failed.
- 噢 是吗 看不出啊
- 链条上的制动器坏了
Could've been any of us.
Just the trolley was round.
任何人都可能被砸中
还好只砸到个推车
- 你没事吧 小姐?
- 我撞到了
Are you all right, miss?
I banged myself.
- 不然更糟
- 说得好!
It could've been worse.
Too bloody right!
I've put in a request for
maintenance for these hydraulics
这些液压装置我已经报修两次了
- 根本没人理
- 我会去查的
twice and nothing's been done.
I'll look into it.
You'll look into it? Oh, he's going
to look into it, lads.
你会查? 噢 各位 他会查的
- 是不是他妈有点晚啊
- 我说了我会查的!
Bit too bloody late for that.
I said I'll look into it!
两月前Curtis出事 现在又来一起?
Curtis two months back and now this?
不行 我要求全面停工
No. I'm calling a general stoppage.
What? Now?
什么? 现在?
Yes, now, Mr Broom.
没错 现在 Broom先生
I've got to look out for my members.
我必须要照顾我的成员们
他们怎么说?
What are they saying?
意外
An accident.
Tracepurcel's called a general
stoppage.
Tracepurcel已经开始全面停工
昨天死人? 今天劳动事故?
Murder yesterday?
An industrial accident today?
天呐 趁公司还在 我们快开会吧
Goodness. We'd better begin
while we still have a company to
discuss.
Where would you like me, Henry?
Under the sod.
- 你想我坐哪 Henry?
- 棺材里
I was that 20 years. If you remember.
20年前我就坐进去了 如果你还记得的话
变得真快啊
So much for infinite variety.
I'll take my usual place,
unless there are any objections.
没人反对的话 我还是坐老位子
Morse.
Morse
关于喝东西的提议
About that drink.
I wondered if you were doing anything
tonight.
不知道你今晚有没有空
洗头发
Washing my hair.
Oh...
在哪? 几点?
Where? When?
Nine? Fox and Hounds?
Sounds great. See you then.
- 九点? 猎狐酒吧?
- 听起来不错 到时见
See you then.
到时见
这生意不错 妈妈 欧洲是未来趋势 Nora
It's a good deal, Mother.
Europe's the future, Nora.
Look at BAC.
看看英国宇航公司
Ah! The entente cordiale!
How very "now"!
啊! 谅解备忘! 多"与时俱进"啊!
Whatever happened to
"Vive la difference"?
那"差异万岁"呢?
听着 如果我们不插一脚 建立伙伴关系
5年 10年后 我们就错失良机了
Look, if we don't get in, establish
partnerships, five, ten years,
we'll have missed the bus.
伙伴关系可以 但是合并?
Partnerships, yes. But a merger?
In my experience,
that's just a polite name
根据我的经验 这不过是换个好听名字的
另一种国会用语罢了
for another kind of congress
altogether
我知道谁会得到好处 相信我
and I know who'll be on top,
believe me.
Harry绝不会同意这个的
Harry would never have stood for it.
It was Harry's idea.
I don't believe you.
- 这就是Harry的主意
- 我不相信你
Believe what you like. It's academic.
爱信不信 问题是这是空谈
If we don't go in with the French
now, this year, we're finished.
如果今年我们不加入法国人的话
我们就完了
完了是什么意思?
What do you mean, finished?
We've sunk everything we have
into the new Standfast.
我们把老本全压在新超快导弹上了
- 而且还有更多的订单
- 反对预期销售
And more besides.
Against projected sales.
What about the Arabs?
那阿拉伯人呢?
他们不是要订36枚导弹吗?
They're about to put in an order
for three dozen, aren't they?
Aren't they?
不是吗?
Hello.
- 你好
Strange to be back here again
after all these years.
多年后再次回到这里感觉有点怪
这里的学生比我记忆中要少
Fewer students than I remember.
I expect nowadays they're all down
the pop-dancing club.
我想现在的学生都去唱歌跳舞的夜店了
- 唱歌跳舞?
Pop dancing?
- 或者其他什么吧
Or whatever it is they do.
那...警察?
So... the police?
If you'd asked me, I'd never have...
You like it?
如果你问我 我绝对想不到...
你喜欢这工作吗?
I like the work.
我挺喜欢的
说实话 我不确定自己是不是合群
To be honest,
I'm not sure that I fit in.
是啊 你总是跟其他人不一样
No. You were never like the rest.
我想跟他们一样 我想我试过了
Well, I wanted to be.
Tried to be, I think.
When?
什么时候?
真的 我试着去喜欢传统爵士 愤青 萨特
I did. I tried to like Trad
and the Angries. Sartre.
French cigarettes.
- 法国烟
- 所以我喜欢你 你很难相处
That's why I liked you.
You were difficult.
你想说的是不同吧?
Different, surely.
Difficult. Definitely.
绝对是难相处
很尴尬
Awkward.
你社交上非常窘
You were all... corners socially.
Ah, well...
And so angry.
- 啊 这样...
- 而且很愤青
与世界为敌
Contra mundum.
特别是老和自己过不去
But yourself, most of all.
I think we've heard quite enough
about me. Tell me about you.
一直都在聊我 说说你的事吧
你是说谈谈Broom家的事吗?
You mean tell you about the Brooms?
That is why you asked me
for a drink.
这才是你约我喝酒的原因
You must be wondering
what's going on.
但你肯定很好奇这是怎么回事吧
我是个忠诚的员工 很谨慎
I'm a loyal employee. Discreet.
- 那就问一个问题
- 是作为警察还是朋友问的?
One question, then.
As a policeman or as a friend?
A friend.
朋友
Have you ever heard any of them
mention a girl called Olive Rix?
你有没有听过他们
提到一个叫Olive Rix的女孩?
没有
No.
Look, I'm sorry how everything
turned out back then.
我很遗憾那时事情变成那样
你本来可以得到更好的
You deserved more.
I doubt that, but...
good of you to say.
我不这么觉得
但是谢谢你的好言语
After all that went the way it did,
事情变成那样之后
I hoped you might look to me
for something.
我还希望你可能会来找我
随便什么都好
Anything.
And then you were gone. Lost.
结果你却走了 失踪了
Why do you wear your hair like that?
你为什么把头发做成这样?
你不喜欢吗?
Don't you like it?
Alice. You don't need to...
Alice 你不需要...
- 我让你想起她了吗?
- 你为什么要我想起她?
Do I remind you of her?
Why would you want to?
If that's what it takes.
如果这样能成功的话
Do I?
我成功了吗?
Are you still in love with her?
你还爱她吗?
- 我不知道
- 那就是爱了
I don't know.
Then you are.
Maybe you could love me too.
也许你也可以爱我
一点点就好
Just a little.
一点点就够了
A little would be enough.
Morse...
噢 我有任务
Oh, I'm on call.
一定要留电话给我
You have to leave a number.
Lenny Frost?
还是离这地方远点的好
So much for
staying away from the place.
Morning, sir.
Thursday.
- 早上好 长官
- 早上好 Thursday
What have we got?
Doctor?
- 有什么发现?
- 医生?
触电致死 雨顺着屋顶漏了一段时间
Electrocuted. Rain's come in through
the roof over a length of time.
积了水
Puddled.
Come into contact with a section
of split electrical cable
碰到了一段裂开的电缆
然后Bob 换句话说这案子里的Lenny
and Bob - or in this case, Lenny -
is no longer your uncle.
就不再一切如意了
(引申自短语Bob's your uncle 一切如意)
His wallet's here.
No question of foul play?
- 他钱包在这儿
- 不是谋杀?
Thankfully, that's a decision
for the coroner.
谢天谢地 那是验尸官要做的判断
但如果让我猜 我会比较倾向于
But were I a betting man,
I'd be more inclined to lay this
设备维护不善所导致
upon the altar of bad maintenance.
Wasn't there another here yesterday?
Near miss at least?
昨天是不是也有类似的事件?
至少侥幸逃脱了?
- 是的 长官
- 那就是运气不好了
Yes, sir.
Misadventure, then.
Unless someone knew he was bound
to pass this way.
除非有人知道他一定会路过这里
他们怎么会知道?
How would they know that?
这些窗户都通到外面 长官
Those windows lead on
to the outside, sir.
如果他是爬窗进出
If that's how he's been
getting in and out,
it would be easy enough
for someone to stage an accident.
那就很容易导演一场意外
我比较关心他过来做什么
I'm more concerned as to what
he was doing here.
可能是蓄意破坏
Sabotage, maybe.
Paying the company back
for how they treated him.
对公司进行报复
I'm more inclined to an accident.
我也觉得是意外
这里的安全记录并不十分好
The safety record here
doesn't inspire confidence.
他口袋里是什么?
What's that in his pocket?
Where did you get this?
What are they, Dr Volk?
- 你从哪弄来这的个?
- 这是什么 Volk博士?
Highly confidential research papers.
高度机密的研究文件
超快导弹的陀螺系统测试和研究结果
Test results and findings concerning
the Standfast's gyroscopic system.
Where would they have come from?
他们是哪来的?
我们大部分文件都放在
Most of our documentation
is held in the archive
in the basement of the offices,
办公室地下室的档案馆里
but this was taken
from this workshop.
但这份是从这个车间里拿走的
Who else would have an interest
in such material?
还有谁会从这类东西里得益?
这属于敏感的商业机密
This is information of
a sensitive commercial nature.
可能是我们的竞争对手?
Our rivals, perhaps?
Beyond that I'm not qualified
to express an opinion.
除此之外 我没有资格发表其他看法
Volk. What's that? German, is it?
Volk 是什么? 德语是吧?
- 在大英工作多久了?
- 18年
Worked long at British Imperial?
18 years.
When would that be? Early '47?
那是什么时候? 47年早期?
What was that all about?
你之前在哪?
It was him and a load more like him
flattened my street.
就是他们这种人炸平了我的街道
I'm sure it wasn't personal.
- 我想这不是他个人意愿
Wasn't it?
- 是吗?
You're too young to remember.
你太年轻不记得了
你在Vexin小姐那没查到什么吧?
I don't suppose you've got any
further with Miss Vexin, have you?
I've spoken to her.
She couldn't shed any light.
我和她谈过 她没说什么
How hard did you push her?
你给她施了多少压?
- 施了我觉得必要的压
As far as I thought necessary.
- 是吗 你排除她嫌疑了吧?
I see. Ruled her out, have you?
The fact she's a looker play any part
in that?
就因为她长得好看?
不是 因为她不是德国人
I based it more on the fact
that she isn't German.
长官...
Sir...
每个人都知道Lenny Frost
对Eustace Kendrick怀恨在心
everyone knew that Lenny Frost had
it in for Eustace Kendrick.
完美的替罪羊
现在他没办法替自己辩护了
A perfect scapegoat. Now he's in no
position to defend himself.
You think someone's trying
to close the case down?
你觉得有人想结案?
Well, don't you?
Who? The Brooms?
- 你不觉得吗?
- 谁呢? Brooms家的人?
怎么可能有人知道
Frost昨晚会来工厂?
How would anyone have known Frost
was at the factory last night?
说不定他是被骗过来的
Perhaps he was lured here.
Who by?
I don't know.
- 被谁?
- 我不知道
But there was ?100 in cash
in his wallet,
但他钱包里有100镑现金
还有一个Rudolph酒店房间号
together with a room number
at the Rudolph Hotel.
Well, why didn't you say so before?
你之前为什么不说?
My country may be about
to spend a great deal of money
我们国家也许会和
大英电机做一笔大生意
with British Imperial Electric.
Despite assurances to the contrary,
除了没有书面担保
rumours of trouble with
the new guidance system
还不断听闻说新制导系统有问题
have continued to reach our ears.
So, Lenny Frost was spying for you?
所以 Lenny Frost是你的探子?
The Prophet, peace be upon him,
teaches us,
穆罕默德 愿他安息 教导我们
"Say what is true, though it may be
bitter and displeasing to people."
"说真话 虽然事实苦涩令人不快"
我们有相似的古话
打消顾虑说实话
We have a not dissimilar saying.
Tell the truth and shame the Devil.
你要知道接收赃物是违法的
You should be aware that to take
receipt of stolen property
is an of fence in law.
As you should also be aware,
Constable Morse,
你也应该知道 Morse警员
我们再不是Lawrence上校身后唯唯诺诺的人了
(阿拉伯起义中英国联络官)
we are not the same little people
Colonel Lawrence left behind.
我们在被殖民时期学了很多
We learned much from
our colonial masters.
背信弃义的Albion?
(英格兰旧称)
Perfidious Albion.
An unkind name to hang upon
a country.
对一个国家来说这名字太刻薄了
But not perhaps wholly undeserved.
但得来不是没原因的
Morse.
It's me.
- Morse
- 是我
Alice.
Alice
你问的那个女孩 Olive Rix
That girl you were asking about -
Olive Rix.
What about her?
她怎么?
Alice Vexin几年前偶然知道了这件事
Alice Vexin came upon it
a few years ago,
but it wasn't until she heard the
name Olive Rix that it made sense.
但一直到她听到Olive Rix这个名字
才想通
- 想通什么?
- 应该就在这附近
What made sense?
It should be around here somewhere.
松树林里的一棵山毛榉
A single beech in a stand of pine.
Single beech, you say?
Mm.
- 你说一棵山毛榉?
- 嗯
Harry跟她断断续续在一起一年吧?
Harry had been knocking about with
her for, what, a year, on and off?
Nothing serious.
Just Harry being Harry.
他不是认真的 玩玩而已
She was a gold-digger.
She might not have had the best
start in life,
- 她是个靠脸骗钱的
- 她的出身虽然不算太好
but at the time she went missing,
she was working hard to make
something of herself.
但她失踪的时候
她一直很努力想为自己创造什么
How was it your brother came to know
Olive Rix?
你弟弟怎么认识Olive Rix的?
有一天我遇到她
在Great Wood骑马的时候
I met her one day.
Hacking out in Great Wood.
我们年纪差不多
都有个哥哥有个弟弟
We were of an age.
One girl amongst two brothers.
- 你们俩交朋友了?
You hit it off?
She was fun.
- 她挺有趣的
She had this - I don't know -
Sara Crewe fantasy.
她幻想自己 我说不清 是Sara Crewe吧
(《小公主》主人公)
异想天开觉得自己爸爸是个
有钱的外国贵族
Some wild idea her father
was a rich, foreign nobleman,
and that one day he'd come
and find her.
有一天会回来找她
如果那是她的梦想
我也没必要戳破它
If that was her dream,
I wasn't about to spoil it for her.
Why did you all deny knowing her?
你们为什么都不承认认识她?
Why not?
为什么要承认?
12年前你们找不到她
现在为什么要旧事重提?
You couldn't find her 12 years ago.
Why rake over it all now?
人们只会传流言蜚语
People would only gossip.
干嘛还要送把柄给他们?
Why give them ammunition?
Never apologise, never explain.
不道歉 不解释
她失踪那天你见过她吗?
Did you see her the day
she disappeared?
More or less everybody from the
Agricultural College had gone home
农学院的学生几乎都回家了
to celebrate the Coronation
with their families.
跟家人庆祝加冕日
But animals are Republican
by temperament.
但是动物就跟共和党人一样使性子
They still need feeding, cleaning,
milking,
它们还是需要有人喂 做清理 挤奶
Vivat Regina or no.
要么就是女王万岁
Olive正好一个人
所以我提出去养猪场帮她
Olive was on her own so I offered
to help her out down at the piggery.
We did a couple of hours,
我们忙了几个小时
and I left her shortly after one
to go back to the house.
1点以后我离开她回家了
那你就是最后一个见过Olive Rix的人了 Broom小姐
Then, you were the last person to
see Olive Rix, Miss Broom.
除了那个和她做爱做之事的人
Apart from whoever,
well... did what they did.
I asked her if she'd like to come to
the party.
我问她要不要来参加派对
She said she couldn't.
I presumed she was meeting someone.
她说不行 我猜她约了人
Eustace Kendrick
Eustace Kendrick.
Did your brother know she was
involved with another man?
你弟弟知道她跟别人有染吗?
If he had, I doubt it would have
troubled him.
就算知道 他应该也不会困扰吧
- 像他爸一样
- 好像你很了解一样
Like father.
Shows how much you know.
天呐 你们不厌倦这样吗?
Christ, God. Aren't you tired of it?
Dickie!
She broke it off with Harry.
- Dickie!
- 她跟Harry分手了
In Great Wood. That afternoon.
就是那天下午在Great Wood
I came on him in the billiard room
later.
我后来在桌球房遇到他
他喝醉了 很失态
He was drunk. Beside himself.
Richard! Please...
- Richard!
- 拜托...
我发现了她
I found her.
她的尸体
Found her body.
Olive Rix.
The morning after the party.
Olive Rix 派对第二天早上
I'd taken the dogs up to Great Wood
to clear my head.
我去Great Wood遛狗 想清醒一下
她就在那 在树林里
And there she was.
In the tree line, just back
from the Half Farthing Field.
从Half Farthing回去的路上
Why didn't you come forward?
你为什么之前不说出来?
And say what?
My brother was a murderer?
说什么? 我弟弟是凶手?
What would you have done?
是你你会怎么做?
- 他承认了?
- 我们没聊过这事
He confessed?
We never spoke of it.
没多说
Not in so many words.
你也许会觉得奇怪
That may sound strange to you.
I knew.
我知道
He knew I knew.
But not saying it out loud...
他知道我知道了 但都没有说出来
Gave you just enough doubt
to live with.
让你活在疑问中
- 你怎么做的?
- 埋了
What did you do?
Fetched a spade.
The police pretty quickly settled on
Eustace Kendrick for it, and er...
警察很快锁定了Eustace Kendrick
Well...
嗯...
- 就这样了
that was that.
- 所以你就这样让一个无辜的人顶罪?
And you let an innocent man
stand suspect?
It's not as if it came to trial.
也没有判刑啊
- 他出国了
- 完全顺了你的意啊
He left the country.
Which suited you.
And when Percy Malleson
came to the firm,
Percy Malleson来公司的时候
you had no idea he was Kendrick?
你不知道他是Kendrick?
How could I? I'd never met him.
- 我怎么知道? 我又没见过他
There were plenty of photos
in the paper.
- 那时候报纸上有很多照片
真是好笑 我又没剪贴本
Funnily enough, I didn't keep
a scrapbook.
But, no, I didn't know it was him.
但是 我确实不知道是他
Who else knew?
Just me.
- 还有谁知道?
- 只有我
We all knew.
Speak for yourself.
- 我们都知道
- 说你自己别说别人
或者说都被怀疑了 除了Estella
Or at least suspected.
Except Estella.
她在闹腾前就回学校了
She was back at school
before the hue and cry began.
So was I. Most of the time.
我也是 大多数时候
没人会怀疑你的 Johnny
No-one ever suspected
it would be you, Johnny.
Something like that
was well beyond your scope.
那种事你做不出来的
Thank you, Dickie.
That was very brave.
谢谢 Dickie 你很勇敢
I knew my boy was still in there
somewhere.
就知道你没变
- 至少可以结案了
- 结案?
Well, at least that's an end to it.
An end to it?
Frost在工厂杀了Eustace Kendrick
Frost killed Eustace Kendrick
at the factory.
Harry Broom杀了Olive Rix
And Harry Broom killed Olive Rix.
And who killed Lenny Frost?
Not who.
- 那谁杀了Lenny Frost?
- 没人
What. Circumstance. Poor
maintenance. It was an accident.
怎么会 因为设备欠缺维护 是个意外
I might live with one dead murderer,
but not a brace.
死一个我可以忍受
死两个忍受不了
Well, what a Detective Constable
can or cannot live with
一个警员是否能忍受
is a matter of rather small account
in the general scheme of things.
比起大局来说太不重要了
And Division won't trouble
the Palace. Morse!
- 这样咱部门也不会给皇室添麻烦了
- Morse!
这冷嘲热讽的态度
That is a very cynical attitude,
and one you should shake off
sooner rather than later.
我建议你越早改掉越好
我可以向你保证 咱部门
I can assure you that
such a consideration
would play no part in
Division's deliberations.
是绝对不会有这种想法的
- 我走了 Thursday
- 是的 长官
Thursday.
Sir.
Better take Mr Broom's statement.
去给Broom先生录个口供吧
You look old, Henry.
你看起来老了 Henry
- 又老又累
Old and tired.
- 我们互相伤害得还不够久吗?
Have we hurt one another
long enough?
辞了董事长职位
Resign the chairmanship.
How can I... now?
怎么辞...现在?
The company...
Has had the best of you.
- 公司...
- 拥有了你最好的年华
也拥有了我的
Of both of us.
You want my agreement to this merger
with the French,
你要我的同意才能跟法国人合并
that's my condition.
这是我的条件
那明天吧
Tomorrow, then.
最后一次董事会
One last board meeting.
All right?
好了?
You don't believe Lenny Frost's death
was an accident any more than I do.
你也跟我一样
不相信Lenny Frost的死是意外
Have you got a better theory?
那你有更好的说法吗?
那就行了 在你想到更好的解释前
最好做好万全准备
Well, then. Until you do, you're
best off keeping your powder dry.
The truth was buried with Olive Rix
12 years ago.
真相12年前跟着Olive Rix埋入土
We're about to stand by and watch it
buried again with Lenny Frost.
如今我们要再次眼睁睁看着它
跟着Lenny Frost重新入土
And in the name of what?
用什么做借口?
Expediency?
权宜之计?
保住皇室脸面?
Sparing royal blushes?
我以为我们宣誓维护的是公众的安宁?
I thought it was the Queen's Peace
we were sworn to uphold?
Someone was coming up as I arrived.
我到的时候正好有人上楼
Can I come in?
我能进来吗?
当然
Of course.
恐怕你不会觉得我是个好的朋友
I'm afraid you won't find me
terribly good company.
如果知道你要来我就整理一下了
I'd have tidied if I'd known.
Are you all right? I was worried.
You sounded awful on the telephone.
你还好吗? 我很担心
电话里面你听起来不怎么好
好像世界末日一样
As if the world were about to end.
只不过是个小小的 还不怎么好的世界
Just a small world,
and not a very good one.
要不要喝一杯? 我这只有威士忌
Do you want a drink?
I've only got Scotch.
Yeah. All right.
嗯 好
You heard about the Brooms?
- 你听说Broom家的事了?
- 我不是来聊Broom家的
I didn't come to talk about
the Brooms.
From comparison with dental records
"失踪女孩遗体寻回"
I can confirm that these are indeed
the remains of Olive Rix.
根据牙齿记录对比
我可以确定这些是Olive Rix的遗骨
Any thoughts as to how she died?
Fractured hyoid would suggest
she was strangled.
- 可以知道她是怎么死的吗?
- 从舌骨骨折情况看她是被勒死的
Not much to speak of by way
of grave goods.
随葬的东西就看不出什么来了
Clothes have rotted away mostly.
衣服基本上都腐烂了
但还有几颗纽扣
But we've a few buttons.
- 她包包上的一对把手
- 这是什么?
Pair of handles from her bag.
What's this?
噢 普通碎石
Oh, general detritus.
Victorian jam pot, probably.
可能是维多利亚时期果酱盅
把小麦从糠皮里挑出来
Winnowing out the wheat from chaff
一直都是个挑战
is always a challenge
after so long in the earth.
Sir?
长官?
Division want us to sign off.
部门要我们结案
- 两件都是吗?
- 两件都是
On both of them?
Both of them.
Lenny Frost for Eustace Kendrick.
Lenny Frost杀了Eustace Kendrick
Eustace Kendrick for Olive Rix.
Eustace Kendrick杀了Olive Rix
Kendrick? 是Harry Broom杀的Olive Rix 长官
Kendrick? It was Harry Broom
killed Olive Rix, sir.
他哥哥都说了
His brother said as much.
I'm advised that
to pursue such a line...
上头说这样的案件...
不符合公众利益
would not be in the public interest.
是吗 你高兴了吗?
I see. You're happy with that?
Happiness doesn't enter into it.
无关高兴与否
It's what Division wants.
这是部门想要的
Nothing can be allowed to interfere
with this missile sale.
不能有任何事件干扰到导弹交易
So the Brooms walk away from it?
All of it?
所以Broom一家就这么脱身了?
一点事没有?
Business as usual. It's never about
what you know, Morse.
- 还照常做生意
- 你知道的并不重要 Morse
It's about what you can prove.
重要的是你可以证明什么
And what about justice?
Or perhaps that doesn't matter.
那正义呢? 还是说这点根本不重要
Olive Rix不过就是个孤儿
Olive Rix was only a Barnardo's girl.
We found her.
We'd never have managed that much
我们找到了她 要不是你坚持查下去
if you hadn't kept digging away.
我们查不出这么多真相
That's not enough.
Sometimes it has to be.
- 这不够
- 有时候必须够
不是每个问题都能有答案
Not every question gets an answer.
学着接受这点才是最难学会的
Learning to live with that
is the hardest lesson there is.
What are you doing
with your Saturday afternoon, then?
那你周六下午要干什么?
- 在家听歌?
- 我买了Roxy剧院的票
Bit of singing, is it? I've
a couple of tickets for the Roxy.
Tickets? Plural?
票? 复数?
What's this? Your little friend?
怎么? 和你朋友一起?
That didn't take long, did it?
很快就在一起了是吧?
You'll be picking out wallpaper
next.
接着要一起选墙纸了吧
I hear you say pictures?
听到你说电影?
有些不错的
It's all right for some.
What you gonna see?
There's a new Bergman.
- 你要去看什么?
- 英格丽褒曼的新片
Oh, yeah? I thought she was cracking
in Casablanca.
是吗? 我觉得她在电影卡萨布兰卡里超美的
票买好了 还有时间去喝一杯
I've got the tickets. We've got time
for a quick drink first.
You've changed your mind?
你改变主意了?
I have.
是的
You don't mean the cinema, do you?
你不是在说电影是吧?
- 没事
- 是吗?
It's all right.
Is it?
No.
不是
是
Yes.
I suppose.
我想是吧
You're not ready. Not yet.
你还没准备好
I'd always be second best.
我只会永远是第二
安慰奖
Consolation prize.
有一次我就很...
I'd have been happy with that...
once.
满足了
The moment passed.
时机过去了
Mm.
他们叫我去工作了
They've called me into work.
好
Right.
Well...
那...
Your father has asked me
to choose his successor.
你们父亲让我帮他选接班人
我把那人的名字写下来装进了信封
I've written that person's name down
and placed it in this envelope.
If we are to be... whole again...
如果我们要再次团结
成为一家人
a family...
I expect my proposal to be seconded
blind, and passed nem con.
我希望你们能全体赞成我
Agreed?
同意吗?
很好 我提议
Very well. Proposed.
同意
Seconded.
Show of hands?
举手表决?
Thank you, Alice.
谢谢 Alice
Congratulations, Estella.
恭喜你 Estella
谢谢
Thank you.
但我还是比较喜欢三人执政
But I'd prefer to think of us
as a triumvirate.
如果我们要发展得更好
我会需要Dickie和Johnny的专业意见
If we are to make a go of it,
I'm going to need all of Dickie
and Johnny's expertise.
我怎么不知道我有
I didn't know I had any.
To which end, the first we need to
get a grip on is this strike.
所以 我们首先要处理的就是这次罢工
Alice, would you have Mr Tracepurcel
and his Works Committee
Alice 你能不能叫Tracepurcel先生
和他的劳资协议委员会
跟我们在车间见?
join us on the factory floor?
英国牛津 去图书馆就几分钟
"Oxford, England.
Just minutes from the libraries
and cloistered colleges
of the city centre,
却避开了市中心喧嚣的大学
游客会很快发现自己已经置身
a visitor will soon find themselves
amidst the white heat of technology
at the British Imperial
Electric Company in Cowley.
Cowley的大英电机科技的白炽中
作为英国超快二号地对空导弹的制造商
他们充满了自豪
Proud manufacturers
of Britain's Standfast Mark Two
surface-to-air missile.
每个人都竭力保证工厂一尘不染
Everyone is doing their best
to make sure the whole place
is spick and span,
迎接皇家视察
and ready to receive
a royal inspection.
等等 Charlie 那里还没擦干净
Hold on, Charlie.
Looks like you've missed a spot.
这就对了!
That's the ticket!
大家都在热烈欢迎一个非常重要的人物!
Here comes the Very Important Person
everyone has turned out to cheer!
没错 就是玛格丽特公主殿下
Yes, it's Her Royal Highness,
the Princess Margaret,
as she arrives on a mission to help
promote British overseas exports.
她此次来访肩负着推动英国海外出口的重任
Having been greeted by
distinguished foreign guests
跟尊敬的外国来宾
和公司高管一阵寒暄后
and senior company executives,
公主殿下还抽出时间
Her Royal Highness also finds time
跟工人们亲切交谈...
to exchange a word or two
with the workers..."
This what you're looking for?
你在找这个?
- 知道这是什么了?
- 不止
Worked out what it is?
More than that.
I think I can take a decent guess
where it came from.
我应该还可以猜出这是哪来的
Tracepurcel先生?
Mr Tracepurcel?
I wonder if I might have a word.
我能跟你谈谈吗
我在等劳工常务委员会
I'm just waiting
on the Works Standing Committee.
- 我要跟管理层开个会
- 不会耽误你多久
I've a meeting with the management.
This won't take long.
I'm hoping there's something
you might be able to help us with.
有件事我希望你能帮我
就是点礼节问题
A matter of etiquette,
as much as anything.
Etiquette?
Yes.
- 礼节?
- 没错
你见公主殿下的时候
When you were presented to
Her Royal Highness,
you weren't wearing your jacket.
- 没有穿外套
- 外套?
My jacket?
Mm.
I think I was.
No, you weren't.
- 我穿了吧
- 你没穿
你早上穿了
You wore it earlier in the day,
but by the time of the royal visit
you'd got rid of it.
但是皇室成员到达的时候你却没穿了
你被新闻媒体拍进了影片
You were caught on film, you see,
by one of the news vans.
And, as luck would have it,
by a photographer from the Mail.
不巧的是 邮报摄影师照了一些照片
You were in shirt sleeves.
你穿的衬衫
我想看看你那天早上穿的外套
I'd like to see the jacket
you were wearing that morning.
就是这件
This is it.
不是 你看看
你那天穿的是双排扣外套
No, the one you had on was
double-breasted, if you'll look.
Yes. No, er... I spilt some oil
on that one.
是哦 呃...我在车间里
On the shop floor.
把油洒到上面了
Eustace Kendrick came to this factory
Eustace Kendrick来这间工厂
想找杀害Olive Rix的凶手
looking for the murderer
of Olive Rix.
他觉得是Broom家的人
你比他更了解这事是吧?
He thought it was one of the Brooms.
You knew better, didn't you?
I had nothing to do with Kendrick.
我跟Kendrick没关系
你知道Kendrick总觉得哪不对头
You knew there was something
not right about Kendrick.
总有什么不对劲
最后你突然发现他是动作计时员
Something that didn't quite ring
true. Eventually you tumbled
he was a time-and-motion man.
是那时候他告诉你他来工厂的真实目的吗?
That when he told why
he really came to the factory?
他可能以为你会同情他
I suppose he thought you'd have
some sympathy for him.
有了机会可以接近管理层
A chance to finally stick it
to the management for once.
But he confided in the one person
who had everything to lose
如果他继续查 就会发现Broom家是无辜的
但他吐露秘密的那个人就会失去一切
if he continued with his digging and
find out the Brooms were innocent.
Look, I don't know this Rix girl,
and I didn't even work here in '53.
我不认识这个叫Rix的姑娘
53年我都没在这上班
No.
没错
你在邮政总局做修理工
You worked for the GPO
as a repairman.
We checked.
我们查了
服务记录上写着加冕日你有工作
According to the service records
you were on call on Coronation Day,
更换Chinon Court旁电线杆上陶瓷绝缘体
replacing ceramic insulators on
telegraph poles out by Chinon Court.
Unfortunately,
Olive Rix also had reason
偏巧Olive Rix那天下午
也去了Great Wood
to be in Great Wood that afternoon.
She and Harry Broom
had just broken up.
她和Harry Broom刚分手了
就算我当时我在 也不能说明什么
Well, even if I was there,
that doesn't prove anything.
也许吧 但你的手太贱了
Not alone, perhaps,
but you've overplayed your hand.
Brenda Werth差点意外丧命的时候
When Brenda Werth was nearly killed,
你以为我们会认为
you thought we'd take it
at face value
if Lenny Frost fell victim
to a similar industrial accident.
Lenny Frost死于类似工伤事故
你需要有人为Eustace Kendrick的死顶罪
You needed someone to take the drop
for Eustace Kendrick's murder.
大家都知道他俩有过节
Everyone knew there was bad blood
between them.
But only you knew how Lenny Frost
came in and out of the factory.
但只有你知道Lenny Frost怎么进出工厂的
那是个意外 叫做维护不当
It was an accident.
It's what they call bad maintenance.
No. It was murder.
不 那叫谋杀
But you made a mistake.
但你犯了个错
我不犯错
I don't make mistakes.
你应该在他进来的时候杀了他
You should have killed him
on the way in,
before he had a chance to steal
the research papers, not the way out.
在他偷出研究文件之前
而不是出去的时候
The electricity didn't turn itself on
在他往返水坑之间
between his first and second goes
through that puddle.
电源不可能自己打开
So now I've killed Lenny Frost?
Mm-hm.
- 所以现在变成我杀了Lenny Frost?
- 嗯
No, I think you're whistling
in the dark, gents.
我觉得你们高兴得太早了 先生们
我们就假设这是真的好了
虽然这不是真的
Let's just say a word of
that's true, which it isn't.
我为什么要选那天杀了Kendrick?
Why would I have killed Kendrick
on a day like that?
With all the police swarming around.
- 周围有这么多警察
- 你没有选择
You had no choice.
Kendrick's contract with the factory
was due to expire.
Kendrick的劳动合同就要到期了
He was desperate to get to
the truth, and time was running out.
他急于查出真相而时间不多了
You had to act and fast.
你必须要尽快行动
The royal visit was the only time
the Brooms have been under
the same roof in ten years.
皇室来访是十年来唯一一次
Broom一家人齐聚一堂的时候
是他唯一可以见到所有人的机会
His only chance
to confront them all together.
That's why he brought a gun to work.
I think he told you he intended to...
所以他才会带枪来上班
我想他告诉了你他打算...
You can think what you like.
You haven't got any proof.
你爱怎么想都行 你没证据
You're right, we haven't,
but we can clear it up now.
你说得没错 我们没有
但我们现在就可以收集
- 你的外套
- 我告诉你了
Your jacket.
I told you.
上面有油 没错
那它在哪儿呢? 我想看看
There's oil on it, yes. Well, where
is it? Because I'd like to see it.
I burnt it.
我烧了
You burnt it?
你烧了?
我烧了
I burnt it.
In my garden. In the incinerator.
就在我花园的焚烧炉里
Are you sure about that?
Yeah.
- 你确定?
- 对
你外套还在这里
Your jacket is still here.
就藏在厂里的某个地方
On the premises.
Hidden away somewhere.
大门口的警察
Police on the front gates?
You passed them with oil on
your jacket, but not paint.
你可以带着油印在他们面前经过
但是油漆印却不行
- 油漆?
- 没错 确切说是白油漆
Paint?
White paint, to be specific.
The door frame of the store cupboard
had been painted that morning,
那天早上仓库橱柜的门框被粉刷了一遍
where you dumped Kendrick's body
after you'd killed him.
就是你杀了Kendrick后弃尸的橱柜
Yeah, your jacket was covered in
paint. Paint? No.
- 是的 你外套沾上了油漆
- 油漆? 没有
这就是为什么你是唯一一个
That's why you were the only man
presented to Her Royal Highness
in his shirt sleeves.
在公主殿下面前穿衬衫的人
You knew no-one would
be on the factory floor
till the visit was over,
你知道访问结束前是不会有人在车间的
所以你把外套和Kendrick的尸体
so you left the jacket in
the store cupboard
一起留在仓库橱柜
直到安全为止
with Kendrick's body,
until the coast was clear.
Only Alice Vexin heard you
when you came to retrieve it,
and raised the alarm.
可是你回去取的时候
被Alice Vexin听到并报了警
Police have been crawling
all over the place since.
那之后这里到处都是警察
You haven't had a chance
to get rid of it.
你没有机会处理掉它
你只能藏起来
The best you could do was to hide it.
I have to admit, it took me a while.
我得说 的确花了我一点时间
Strange?
Was it where I thought it was?
Mm-hm.
- 是在我想的那个地方找到的吗?
- 嗯
Well, you two are clever buggers,
aren't you?
你俩挺聪明啊?
I thought the inspection pit would
be the perfect place to hide it.
我还以为藏在检修坑是最完美的
那Olive Rix呢?
And Olive Rix?
那是怎么回事?
What was that?
Just an itch you had to scratch?
难忍之痒?
我做的可都是她想要的
Oh, I didn't do anything
she didn't want.
Strange?
You've got to admit,
你得承认
我还是耗了你们很多时间吧?
I give you a good run around,
though, eh?
12年呢
12 years. Ooh.
How did you work out
where I put the jacket?
你是怎么想到我外套的藏身地的?
我没有
I didn't.
I thought it was Richard...
all these years.
这么多年我都以为是Richard
The poison's out now.
败类清除了
长官
Sir.
Well...
嗯...
it should make for a lively meeting
with the Chief Constable.
应该可以跟局长开个很刺激的会了
You might want to mention
Constable Morse's part, sir.
你也许会想提一提Morse警员的功劳 长官
当然
Yes.
Well, if the...
如果...
如果有机会的话
if the opportunity arises.
Carry on.
继续努力
Want me to run you back?
要我送你回去吗?
走吧
Go on, then.
Are you doing anything tonight?
今晚有节目吗?
No.
没有
我要去吃炸鱼薯条
I was after going a cod
and two penn'oth.
Glad of the company
if you'd like to join me.
如果你愿意一起的话我会很高兴
怎么? 不吃三明治?
What? No sandwiches?
On a Saturday? Talk sense.
周六还吃? 别说胡话
Subtitles by MemoryOnSmells
http://UKsubtitles.ru.
Resync: Xenzai  www.subscene.com